<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="xml/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xsl/html/teihtml-teic.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "M:\Transcription\DTD\arrowmont.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="arm03020012000">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter]  Sept. 19, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Responsible for machine-readable version</resp>
                    <name>Young, Philip</name>
                    <name>Lepczyk, Tim</name>
                    <name>Dyson-Smith, Bridger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts, Archives Collection</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Gatlinburg, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Arrowmont School of Arts and Crafts
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>556 Parkway
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>PO Box 567
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Gatlinburg, TN 37738
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2006</date>
                <idno type="SPCID">arm03020012000</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>Digital Image Copyright (c) 2005. The University of Tennessee Libraries. All Rights Reserved. 
                        For permission to use, contact: Great Smoky Mountains Regional Project, The University of Tennessee 
                        Libraries, Knoxville, TN</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc describes analog material, NOT the collection from whi1ch the letter was taken.  http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html#HD3 -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>[Letter]  Sept. 19, 1919, [Gatlinburg, Tennessee to] family</title>
                    <date value="1919-09-19">Sept. 19, 1919</date>
                    <author>
                        <name>Sturley, Ruth</name>
                    </author>
                    <extent>15p</extent>
                    <note type="summary">Weekend trip via Little Pigeon River into <sic corr="North">Nort</sic> Carolina preparing for the school &amp; community fair.</note>
                    <note type="box">3</note>
                    <note type="folder">2</note>
                    <note type="document">arm03020012000</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="3"></editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Local Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Living Conditions</item>
                        <item>Food</item>
                        <item>Landscape</item>
                        <item>Mountains</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="abstract">
                <pb ref="arm03020012001" seq="01"/>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Weekend trip via Little Pigeon River into <sic corr="North">Nort</sic> Carolina preparing for the school &amp; community fair.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb ref="arm03020012002" seq="02"/>
                <head>
                    <date value="1919-09-19"> Sept. 19, 1919</date>
                </head>
                    <p>
                        <del>Dearest family another whole week has flown by and I&apos;m behind again with my letter to you 
                        and as usual just <hi1 rend="underscore">reams</hi1> to write about. Jane&apos;s grand long letter came yesterday (Monday) 
                        and was brimming over with activity. Seems to me you all are having a gay giddy time &amp; so much as is doing in 
                        Tacoma! The papers came today &amp; were much enjoyed.</del></p>
                <p><del>It will be grand for pa to have a trip to California &amp; hope he starts soon. Have been thinking about that sweater of 
                        yours Jane &amp; would like to buy it <sic corr="off">of</sic> you I guess I&apos;ll need one after all as this green coat is 
                        rather big to wear all the time the girls say one lives in a sweater at school. I mean what I say about <hi1 rend="underscore">buying</hi1> 
                        it &amp; won&apos;t take it otherwise. Hope my registered letter with check arrived O.K.</del></p>
                <p><del>The kodaks are awfully nice and was so pleased to get them. Virginia May looks like the other two </del><pb ref="arm03020012003" seq="03"/><del>
                        can&apos;t realize where I&apos;m living even yet it seems like a dream A big map hangs in the schoolroom of the U.S. &amp; 
                        <abbr expan="Washington">Wash.</abbr> is certainly a long ways across from here Don&apos;t look at it! Ask Arthur about taking 
                        a time exposure with my kodak <unclear reason="illegible" resp="tl">Premo No. F</unclear> you know there is a place that 
                        you set for a <hi1 rend="underscore">&quot;time&quot;</hi1> but do not know what else to do as I did not bring my book of 
                        directions <hi1 rend="underscore">foolishly</hi1>! Would like to take some interiors of the house &amp; school.</del></p>
                <p>My last was written Wednesday Did I tell you that I made a batch of Scotch cake that p.m. after school and how good it was? 
                    1 lb. of flour - 1/2 lb. of butter - 1/2 teaspoon baking powder - 2/3 cup sugar - 1 teaspoon vanilla It is so dry you have to work it 
                    a long time &amp; then take little pieces &amp; pat into shape for the pan but its the real stuff! Try it! Our party Thursday night 
                    was a great success began a little after 7 &amp; stopped about 9:15 We played two games the first was making animals 
                    with needle and thread on squares of cloth 2nd was the drawing <pb ref="arm03020012004" seq="04" n="02"/>of various objects on a 
                    blackboard from a baby to a <del>bird&apos;s</del> bird&apos;s nest like the game you suggested Jane They both went 
                    off beautifully too. About twenty five came all ages.</p>
                <p>The weather Friday a.m. was awfully queer a strong <abbr expan="mountain">mt.</abbr> wind blowing &amp; prospects of rain 
                    everyone said. However we went on with our preparations for the trip - Evelyn got back during the morning from Alabama &amp; 
                    was pleased to have us go as she has not really felt equal to taking the trip herself - We closed school at 2 half an hour 
                    earlier than usual &amp; rushed home &amp; got into our costumes - Abbie wore brown corduroy skirt &amp; flannel shirt - 
                    Emily green <abbr expan="corduroy">cord.</abbr> skirt &amp; niddy and I&apos;ve 
                    my riding skirt khak<del>h</del>i niddy &amp; green tie. We started out in our hats (Panama) but soon discarded 
                    them! Mr. C. had packed up everything during the p.m. very neatly (army training) &amp; came up with Dan &amp; the hack about 
                    2:30 - By 3 we were off. Guess we were criticized <pb ref="arm03020012005" seq="05"/>too for going by <hi1 rend="underscore">some</hi1>! 
                    Stopped &amp; got Mrs. Reagan. She is &quot;going on 29&quot; &amp; has a daughter about 14! One of the early marriages of 
                    this region! We drove on up <add place="supralinear">to</add> Forks of the River &amp; then took the road to the Sugar Lands right up 
                    the one Fork of Little Pigeon in the ruts. It was a rough road but worse awaited us - After bumping along cheerfully in the sunshine 
                    for the predictions of rain came to naught we arrived at two roads &amp; following little Emily&apos;s positive directions took the upper 
                    which after a mile or more of traveling we discovered was the wrong one. At a lone store we were directed to a shortcut to the right 
                    road. Dan meanwhile had had rambunctious fits of backing &amp; general stubbornness so we got out &amp; left Mr. C. to entire 
                    management of hack &amp; beast over the awful <del>road</del>
                    <add place="supralinear">road</add> that confronted 
                    us. Really in places great boulders like steps <gap reason="illegible" resp="tl"></gap> and again just lying imbedded in the middle of the 
                    road or <pb ref="arm03020012006" seq="06" n="03"/>at one side made it seem impossible that the hack would ever survive the jolts &amp; 
                    wrenches! And sure enough one of the shafts did break off. Getting wire at the store poor Mr. C. fixed it back in place &amp; soon
                    bumped along again while we girls plodded along in the rear <hi1 rend="underscore">giggling</hi1>! (Tom <sic corr="Cambell's">Camel&apos;s</sic> 
                    wife was sick so he couldn&apos;t go after all.) Then we came to our road &amp; a farm where were some people clustered at the barn 
                    to the road and as we discovered helping a drunken mountaineer along his way. He saw our <sic corr="conveyer">conveyaer</sic> &amp; 
                    immediately wanted to ride and meeting no response began to curse violently. His words were soon lost as we hustled on &amp; he 
                    was too drunk to hurry &amp; overtake us. This is the first victim to moonshine that I&apos;ve seen. Sugar Lands is the heart of &amp; soul 
                    of the moonshine region however &amp; stills are everywhere they say - sugar is always very scarce there! <pb ref="arm03020012007" seq="07"/>
                    Dan continued to be uncertain at moments &amp; the road rough so after another mile or so we decided to leave the hack at the side of 
                    the road - put our packs on his back &amp; continued on foot. Poor Dan he surly was a beast of burden when we got through fixing 
                    him - A big pack hung on either side &amp; one in the middle - our hats pinned gaily on top - a lantern hanging on one side - axe on 
                    another - and the girls&apos; little bags dangling also. A cabin was at the side of the road where we elected to stop &amp; we went in &amp; 
                    asked permission to leave our harness &amp; bought some awfully good apples <sic corr="off">of</sic> them too. We explained 
                    to the two women who we were &amp; where we were going. They were as communicative as most of them are with strangers - constant &amp; persistant questioning will finally get the 
                    desired information. We pushed on until just about dark stopping in <pb ref="arm03020012008" seq="08" n="04"/>a school yard - the Bracken school 
                    at present not used. A small one room building of logs primitive in the extreme - benches &amp; no desks for equipment.</p>
                <p>We built up a fire &amp; in the light of our lantern &amp; the stars got supper - Had cold fried chicken - bread peanut butter - coffee &amp; cake. 
                    It tasted mighty good too. Then picking up our various articles &amp; putting them in the school house in case of rain we rolled up in our 
                    blankets &amp; lay down on the ground under the stars. Mrs. Reagan - Abbie &amp; I having never slept out in this fashion 
                    before did not really <hi1 rend="underscore">sleep</hi1> much - Sleeping in one&apos;s clothes even to 
                    shoes seemed queer &amp; the ground was hard!! But I would not have missed the experience. A dog prowled around a couple 
                    of times &amp; we girls fearing for our precious food got up &amp; examined it &amp; safely shut the schoolhouse door. Don&apos;t 
                    know how many times Abbie &amp; I sat up &amp; fixed our blankets - lost count. About 5:30 we got up &amp; went down a steep 
                    trail to the river <pb ref="arm03020012009" seq="09"/>a wildly picturesque spot - enormous boulders jumbled together &amp; the water so cold 
                    &amp; clear rushing around &amp; over them. Got a picture of it which I hope proves good. Our breakfast consisted of coffee - bacon - 
                    fried eggs &amp; toast. We discovered that our coffee which had tasted queer the night before had been creamed with juice from a 
                    can of &quot;weinies&quot;. In the dark it had looked like condensed milk can you know! 
                    Washing greasy dishes in a cold river at the foot of a steep trail was quite thrilling but Abbie &amp; I did &amp; in the course of time 
                    we were packed <add place="supralinear">&amp;</add> on our way even to the lantern 
                    Dan behaved beautifully as a pack horse &amp; went plodding along all morning over the steep places without one objection even 
                    though the fords of which there were half a dozen - I do not enjoy crossing a stream by leaping from rock to rock but made the trip 
                    successfully in my big boots anyway. <pb ref="arm03020012010" seq="10" n="05"/>We ambled along getting higher &amp; higher till we came 
                    to Jo Cole&apos;s cabin where Mrs. Cole greeted us. This is the last house on the way - except for cabins put up especially 
                    for campers. Buford Cole a youngster about 13 came along with us the rest of our trip as guide. It was beautiful through the 
                    forests so wild and untouched the river part of the time close <abbr expan="with">w</abbr> the trail &amp; then way below 
                    &amp; rocky as always - like most of the trail. About 11 we reached the cabin <add place="supralinear">where</add> we planned to spend 
                    that night. So we unpacked faithful Dan &amp; got lunch - There were two cabins in one of which was a stove so we had an easy time 
                    frying our bacon &amp; apples. As we found some &quot;roasting ears&quot; of corn we boiled them &amp; had quite a spread. 
                    About noon we left everything neatly put away &quot;in the house&quot; &amp; armed with kodak - shotgun &amp; chocolate we start 
                    for the last climb to the <pb ref="arm03020012011" seq="11"/>top of Smoky. It was not very steep but quite a steady climb for about an 
                    hour and three quarters. Then we arrived! A broad green &amp; grassy dip between two low hills &amp; ahead of us blue hazy mountain 
                    ranges of North Carolina rising one above the other about five of them. Even as we looked they became blotted out by mist which rolled 
                    nearer &amp; nearer till we were covered by fog &amp; in a down pour of rain. We crossed the boundary into <abbr expan="North Carolina">N. C.</abbr> 
                    &amp; huddled under a dense growth of small beech trees for half an hour &amp; 
                    ate chocolate. Then it let up &amp; we walked on down half a mile or so into the state &amp; then as we were dampish turned our 
                    faces toward Tennessee again &amp; before we knew it were back home again where we were glad to take off our wet niddies &amp; 
                    wear our dry sweaters the rest of the day. The shower soon arrived after we did so we sat by the cheerful fire &amp; played cards 
                    awhile - The next excitement was the disappearance of Dan - Mr. C. started <pb ref="arm03020012012" seq="12" n="06"/>in search of him with 
                    Buford &amp; in the course of a mile or so found him headed down the road for home. He was brought back &amp; securely fastened 
                    as you can guess. For supper that night we had baked potatoes which we had put in the oven that a.m. - warmed corn bread (am 
                    growing very fond of it) &amp; bacon &amp; rest of our chicken &amp; cake. The downpour was such that we girls slept in the cabin 
                    that night. There was a sort of mattress of corn husks on the floor which served as bed. We four lay cross wise &amp; just had room 
                    rolled tightly in our blankets. It was much more comfortable than the ground too. Buford &amp; Mr. Cresswell had the other house with 
                    Dan tethered for safe keeping to the side. Mr. C. was awfully nice all through the trip &amp; had sort of a hard position in a way - the 
                    only man &amp; four women so think he deserves a medal. We were up about 6 and had fried potatoes with our bacon &amp; eggs 
                    &amp; toast! Best meal <pb ref="arm03020012013" seq="13"/>yet we decided. Then began the usual packing &amp; we were started 
                    homeward about 8:30. It was quite clear &amp; no rain fell all morning - We stopped at the Coles again. They may send their four 
                    youngsters to our school soon. <add place="supralinear">One of</add> Dan&apos;s shoes came off &amp; he developed a slight limp 
                    but aside from that &amp; the slipping off of our packs &amp; a broken egg we got to the old schoolhouse without mishap - Abbie&apos;s 
                    hat which hat mysteriously dissapeared on the way up was discovered to have been picked up by the little Cole girl who wore it to 
                    Sunday School. We met her on the way &amp; Abbie presented her with the hat. She was tickled to death I know but of course 
                    wouldn&apos;t show it. Sunday School was held in the old school &amp; we wondered if our nine eggs which we had left for safe 
                    keeping in the ancient stove would still be there. But they were &amp; gathering them up &amp; stowing them in various pockets on 
                    we went &amp; at last came to the old hack &amp; how glad we were to see it. As it was after noon we decided to eat our 
                    lunch <pb ref="arm03020012014" seq="14" n="07"/>by the roadside then &amp; there. We got some corn bread from the people in the 
                    house at the roadside - a bushel of their good apples - our harness &amp; after while were started on the last lap of the return trip. 
                    We came to a <del>whole</del> great grape vine &amp; gathered as many wild grape clusters as could reach. This 
                    was our last delay until we reached Gatlinburg about 3 - sunburned - dirty &amp; pleased with ourselves &amp; adventures. Evelyn 
                    &amp; Aunt Lizzie welcomed us - How we <sic corr="reveled">revelled</sic> in the hot water &amp; clean clothes! Our supper tasted 
                    awfully good too - hot chocolate - beans - jelly etc. We wound up by going to <hi1 rend="underscore">dear</hi1> <abbr expan="Baptist Young Person&apos;s Union">B.Y.P.</abbr>
                    in the <abbr expan="evening">eve</abbr> &amp; then to bed!</p>
                <p>Well since then it&apos;s been <hi1 rend="underscore">fair</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">fair</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">fair</hi1>. 
                    Have been drilling my girls - getting maps - papers &amp; a few drawings ready - cleaning up at school etc. Yesterday just before 
                    dismissing at noon I lit into the youngsters about several things - letting the room get so <pb ref="arm03020012015" seq="15"/>untidy etc. &amp; 
                    during the noon intermission they got busy so when I went over at 12:45 the room had been swept &amp; fresh flowers put every where! 
                    After school a bunch of the girls with Emily &amp; me went after ferns up Baskin&apos;s 
                    then went to school &amp; planted them in old trees &amp; pails &amp; put them in the baskets - nearly a dozen of greens - lovely 
                    big ones - sword - maiden hair &amp; a fine fronded fern prettier but similar to our brakes. In the <abbr expan="evening">eve.</abbr> was 
                    a community meeting about the fair at school which we all attended of course. Tonight there was an 
                    entertainment given by a Mr. Russell ventriloquist &amp; musician. He goes around the county giving these entertainments - 10 &amp; 
                    15 cent admissions! Bought a copy of a song he sang. (5¢) his own composition &amp; very similar to the songs that I heard at 
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">the</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">sing</hi1>! Am sending it - it&apos;s rich.</p>
                <p>Must stop as it&apos;s late and a busy day is before me tomorrow.</p>
                <p>With just oodles of love to one and all</p>
                <p>Ruth</p>
                <p>Tuesday - Great trees of rhododendrons all over <abbr expan="mountains">mts.</abbr>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">dense</hi1>
                    <hi1 rend="underscore">dense</hi1> sample leaf.</p>
                <p>Sept. 23, 1919</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
